Finding Aid for American National Red Cross, Washtenaw County Chapter Records 1916-1976
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
American National Red Cross, Washtenaw County Chapter records 1916-1976
American National Red Cross. Washtenaw County Chapter.
History; board minutes and other records of the chapter, and of the Ann Arbor and Ypsilanti branches; activities files detailing work of chapter in matters of public health and wartime home services; newsletters; scrapbooks and newspaper clippings; and photographs.
852163; Bf 2; BF Outsize
4 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were deposited by the Washtenaw County Chapter of the American Red Cross (donor no. 1870 )
The record group is open for research.
Red Cross activity existed in Washtenaw County on an informal basis in the communities of Ann Arbor, Ypsilanti, Chelsea, Manchester, Milan, and Saline before 1917. The Ann Arbor Chapter, as it was originally titled, sought and received national recognition in February 1917. Red Cross efforts in Ypsilanti achieved similar recognition in March 1917.
Formal organization of the Red Cross continued as the United States entered World War I. In May 1917, the commissioner of the Red Cross in Michigan reported to the chapters the growing preference for administrative control on the county level. A charter for the Washtenaw County Chapter of the American Red Cross was issued soon after in June 1917. The community chapters were thereafter called branches.
Early activities of the Washtenaw County Chapter included sewing, knitting, and preparing surgical dressings. A Civilian Relief Committee was organized in October 1917 to assist families of servicemen. These efforts led to the formation of the Home Service Committee in 1918. Following World War I, this committee worked to assist returning servicemen seeking employment, financial security, and government allowances.
During the Depression years, the Washtenaw County Chapter distributed clothing, government grain, and other relief supplies. Family casework and the rehabilitation of servicemen were priorities at this time.
The years of World War II saw both the continued success of established programs and the introduction of new efforts. The Junior Red Cross, which began in 1919 and was active throughout the Depression years, worked to collect articles for servicemen in the 1940s. Demands upon the Home Service department remained strong throughout the Korean War. Also, first aid training, in 1917, increased after Pearl Harbor, as the general safety program grew.
Activities which commenced during the War years included the blood program, which began in 1940 when the American Red Cross promoted the separation of blood plasma from red and white blood cells on a large scale. Other programs germinating during these years were the Motor Service (1940), which assisted in the transport of volunteers and the delivery of materials; the Canteen (1942), which served coffee and donuts to draftees and blood donors, and the Arts and Skills Corps (1945), which assisted in the rehabilitation of disabled veterans.
During the 1950s, major concerns were Hungarian relief and the polio epidemic. Also during the 1950s, the Washtenaw County Chapter began to consider the necessity of new headquarters, as the organization's location in Nickels Arcade was cramped and poorly ventilated. A campaign was launched to raise funds to cover projected construction costs. On October 8, 1963, the new headquarters on 2729 Packard Road was dedicated.
A second significant celebration occurred four years later, when, on June 29, 1967, the Washtenaw County Chapter celebrated its 50th anniversary. Activities which remained strong throughout the 1960s and early 1970s included the instruction of first aid techniques, the Water Safety Program, and the Blood Drive.
The records of the Washtenaw County Chapter of the American Red Cross span the years from 1916 to 1975 and document the history of the first fifty years of the Red Cross in Washtenaw County. One may trace the growth of this organization from the early meetings at the home of Dr. Louis P. Hall on Hill Street in Ann Arbor in 1917 through the war efforts to the successful building campaign and the fiftieth anniversary celebration in 1967. Best documented are the administrative activities and the Home Service efforts of the county chapter. This record group is divided into five series: History, Administration, Activities, Informational, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
American National Red Cross. Ann Arbor Branch.; American National Red Cross. Washtenaw County Chapter.; American National Red Cross. Ypsilanti Branch.; Charities--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Nursing--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Public health--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Women--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; World War, 1939-1945--War work.
Subjects:
American National Red Cross. Washtenaw County Chapter.; War work--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Women--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; World War, 1939-1945--Social aspects--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; World War, 1939-1945--War work.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- History
  The first series, History, contains several versions of a manuscript chronicling the activities of the Washtenaw County Chapter from its early days during World War I to the fiftieth anniversary celebration in 1967.
  - Original Version (Box 1)
  - Later Versions (Box 1)
- Administration
  The second series, Administration, is divided into four subseries. The first subseries contains the records of the Ann Arbor Branch of the American Red Cross from 1916 to 1936. Included here are general record books kept from 1916 to 1930. These volumes are rich in the early history of Red Cross activities in Washtenaw County. Board meeting minutes of the Ann Arbor Branch from 1931 to 1936 follow.
  The second, and largest, of the four subseries within the Administration series contains the records of the Washtenaw County Chapter. Here are record books in which the organization interfiled Board Meeting minutes, annual reports, and financial statements kept during the years from 1923 to 1942. After these years, the Board meeting minutes (1943-1969), the Executive Committee minutes (1950-1969), and the annual meeting records are filed separately. Located within those files devoted to the annual meetings are annual meeting minutes, printed reports distributed to attending members, and annual meeting programs. This subseries closes with general correspondence from 1928 to 1937.
  The Administration series of this record group closes with a third and a fourth subseries devoted to the administrative records of the Ypsilanti and Manchester Branches, respectively. The third subseries consists of an early membership list from 1918 and five ledger books from the Ypsilanti Branch, while the fourth subseries contains a proposed agenda for a Manchester Board meeting held in January of 1959.
  - Ann Arbor Branch
    - Records
      - 1916-1917 (Box 1)
      - 1918-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920-1925 (Box 1)
      - 1926-1930 (Box 1)
    - Board Minutes
      - 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County Chapter
    - Records
      - 1923-1932 (Box 1)
      - 1933-1940 (Box 1)
      - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - Board Minutes
      - 1943-1944 (Box 1)
      - 1948-1960 (Box 1)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee Minutes
      - 1950-1954 (Box 1)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 1)
      - 1965-1966 (Box 1)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - Membership List (Box 1)
    - Annual Meetings
      - Minutes 1946, 1948-1949, 1951-1971 (Box 1)
      - Reports to Members 1955-1963, 1968 (Box 1)
      - Programs
        - 1955, 1957-1961 (Box 1)
        - 1962, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports 1948, 1951-1961, 1969, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Ypsilanti Branch
    - Membership List 1918 (Box 2)
    - Financial Records
      - Book No. 1. January 1, 1942-June 30, 1944 (Box 2)
      - Book No. 2. July 1, 1944-December 31, 1945 (Box 2)
      - Book No. 3. January 1, 1946-December 31, 1946 (Box 2)
      - Book No. 4. January 1, 1947-March 31, 1948 (Box 2)
      - Book No. 5. April 1, 1948-September 30, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Manchester Branch
    - Board Meeting Minutes 1959 (Box 2)
- Activities
  The third series in this record group, Activities, begins with the records of the Public heath Nursing Service and the Rural Public Health Service accumulated during the early years of the organization. Next are records documenting the Home Service work of the County Chapter. Located here are files containing historical accounts of the Home Service department, records of the Civilian Relief Committee, promotional materials, and correspondence. Also contained in the Activities series are subseries devoted to volunteer programs and recognition ceremonies, the new headquarters building campaign launched in the later 1950s, and several Michigan State Red Cross conferences.
  - Public Health Nursing Service
    - Monthly Reports 1919-April 1921, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports 1919-1922 (Box 2)
  - Rural Public Health Nursing
    - Monthly Reports May 1921-June 1922 (Box 2)
  - Home Services
    - History (Box 2)
    - Civilian Relief Committee 1918-1919 (Box 2)
    - Promotional Material (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1919-1958 (Box 2)
  - Volunteer Work
    - Awards Ceremonies
      - 1956, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
      - 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Roll of Honor 1971, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Friendly Visit Program (Box 2)
  - Building Campaign
    - Campaign Records 1960-1963 (Box 2)
    - Building Plans (Box 2)
    - Ground Breaking Ceremony October 11, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Conferences
    - Michigan State Conferences 1958, 1959, 1961, 1963 (Box 2)
- Informational
  The fourth series in this record group, Informational, contains several issues, 1970-1976, of the newsletter Current. Newspaper Clippings and Photographs complete the series. Although the participants in the photographs are not identified, the nature of the Red Cross activities depicted is clear.
  - Newsletters 1970-1976 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  The record group closes with a series of Scrapbooks. These document the activities of the Washtenaw County Chapter from the late 1930s to the early 1950s. Some scrapbooks are devoted to specific concerns of the chapter, such as the Motor Corps or Accident Prevention. There is also an exchange album which tells of life in the United States and was prepared in 1934 by the Junior Red Cross of the Burton School in Grand Rapids to be sent to a recipient school abroad.
  - 1930-1935 (Box 3)
  - 1934 (Exchange Album) (Box 3)
  - 1937-1942 (Box 3)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - 1941-1943 (Motor Corps) (Box 3)
  - 1942-1944 (Ypsilanti Press) (Box 3)
  - 1943 (Box 4)
  - 1943-1944 (Accident Prevention) (Box 4)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 4)
  - 1944-1946 (Accident Prevention) (Box 4)
  - 1946-1948 (Volume 1)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 4)